Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning
about the properties of acids and bases.
Now, acids and bases are some of the most
common chemicals that we use, and not
only in chemistry, but also in biology.
So this tends to be one of the more
important types of chemicals that
you learn about to prepare yourself,
whether it's for chemistry, biology, Um,
chemical engineering or in the health
sciences, acids and bases are all around
us, especially in our everyday life.
So when it comes to acids and bases,
the first thing that's all about is
exactly how can we classify them?
Now, it all started around in the late
1800s when a famous scientist named
Arrhenius, um, who was awarded the
Nobel prize back in 1903, Um, for this
is that he was examining the properties
of different aqueous solutions.
So meaning different types of
chemicals that were dissolved in water.
And the one thing that he
noticed was that acids, acids
are substances that dissociate or
break apart when they are in water.
Now, when those things break, they
tend to produce H plus in water, which
is one of the most important parts.
So being that it produces, it produces
H plus, uh, that denotes an acid and
a base is something that dissociated
and produced hydroxide or OH minus.
Now, one of the things that you
generally learn in your chemistry course
is when you're naming acids, you're
always looking for an H plus at the
beginning of the formula, whereas a
base, you usually traditionally learn
that you have an OH minus at the end.
Now, being that we're talking about ions,
well, this all relates to electrolytes.
So all of these different acids and
bases can be classified as electrolytes,
both strong and weak electrolytes,
because when they dissolve, they are
ionized, meaning they can conduct
electricity as a result, right?
A lot of the batteries that you have
in your different devices generally
have acid base characteristics.
If you ever look at your car
battery under your hood, you might
notice that it says that it's corro
that it's very corrosive on it.
And then it might even say on the
inside of it, there's sulfuric acid.
Same thing if you ever have like
a, let's say a battery in the
back of like a device, one of the
removable ones, you might see that
it might get battery acid on it.
And that's telling you, Hey, this is
leaking out and that it is corroding.
Now, when it comes to electrolytes,
the whole idea is that essentially what
we are doing is we're taking something
like, let's say HCl, which is an acid.
And if we are to, let's say, throw
that into water, it will dissociate.
So the way that we would write
that, it was, we would say, Hey,
we have HCl, this is aqueous.
We would draw a dissociation reaction,
just saying that they are breaking apart.
in water and we are going to
be making H plus and Cl minus.
And this is all going off of
solubility rules when it comes to
those different acids and bases.
So being that it generated H plus that's
being surrounded by waters, this tells
you this made H plus that increased.
So this is an acid based on
the Arrhenius acid definition.
Now, from there, if I go to an Arrhenius
base, for example, with sodium hydroxide,
Well, it's the same general idea.
If I were to throw sodium hydroxide
in water, well, what's going to happen
is that it's going to dissociate
or break into its individual ions,
which are Na plus and OH minus.
And they are both going
to be aqueous as a result.
They will be solvated by water,
which will cause them to dissociate.
And this is what we refer to when we
talk about different electrolytes.
In solution, let's take a look at some
different types of chemical reactions
that acids and bases are capable of doing
and some other definitions behind this.
Acids and bases are generally responsible
for some of the most, some of the most
dangerous and some of the most beautiful
reactions that we can see in science.
Um, many of them have to do
by how you work biologically.
Um, but one of the most common ones is
neutralization, meaning that when you
add an acid and you mix it with a base.
Uh, what is going to be happening is
the hydrogen ion from the hpl, from
the acid from h plus and hydroxide,
OH minus from the base, they will
combine and neutralize to form water.
Now the other part of the reaction
is the cat ion in the ion in
the reaction will make a salt.
So every time you neutralize
something, you make a salt.
and water.
So if I were to go, if I was going
to be adding, let's say HCl or
hydrochloric acid to sodium hydroxide,
well, what are we going to be making?
We're going to make a water and salt
because this is a double displacement
reaction inside bonds with outside, right?
The inside bonds together
making a salt or NACL, right?
Cation is always first.
And then the outside bonds
together, making H2O, or water.
So this is the way that we would
generally define an acid base reaction.
Now this might be one specific
illustration of this, but we
can kind of follow the general
definition for acids and bases.
It's common to see where we'll use, put
an H out front to represent an acid.
The X represents the anion or the
negative ion that's connected to and
that's going to be reacting with a
base that has a hydroxide component.
We'll trade the different pieces.
to make water and salt as a product.
So this is one of the major
types of reactions when it
comes to acid based chemistry.
Let's look at some more definitions.
Definition was not a
complete picture, right?
H plus is generally the way that
we do describe acids, especially
when we work with the pH scale.
However, it was slightly incomplete.
The thing about acids and
bases is that they only explain
different types of molecules
that contain H plus and OH minus.
meaning this definition is very limited.
There's other different types of acid.
There's different types
of bases specifically that
don't follow this definition.
So in order to explain this better in
terms of solution, especially for a
molecule like ammonia, which is one
of the most common weak bases that
we, that we are exposed to generally.
Um, it doesn't follow this definition.
It doesn't donate a proton.
However, what it can do is
it can receive one, right?
It doesn't generate H plus or generate
OH minus, but it can accept one.
So what this definition instead of the
other one, so two different definitions.
So Arrhenius acid bases were
increasing H plus and OH minus.
The Bronsted Lowry definition is that
an acid will donate a proton, and a base
will accept or receive that proton, so
it's all about giving and receiving.
So whenever we have an acid, right, it
leads with H and what it's trying to do,
it's kind of start trying to play catch.
Give that proton away.
So whenever we have that, one
thing to kind of remind ourselves
is, well, what is H plus?
This is what we would call a proton.
Now, why is that the case?
Why do we call it a proton?
Well, you got to think back to
the base from long time ago with
regular basic chemistry and it all
had to do with, well, if you have a
neutral hydrogen atom, it contained
one proton and one electron, right?
And it's spot number one on the periodic
table, meaning one proton, one electron.
one electron.
However, when it's H plus, that
means it loses that one electron.
So what is left?
If it lost the one electron, the only
thing left is that one single proton.
And that's why we call an H plus a proton.
So whenever we are talking about a
bronze, that Lowry acid, we talk, we
refer to that as a proton donor, right?
So it received, or so
it's donating that H plus.
Whereas a base is a proton
acceptor, all right?
So that's one of the common
ways that we describe this.
Let's look at some examples of trying
to label proton donors and acceptors.
With all this, the whole idea to
label an acid and base is figuring out
what will donate a proton to a base.
what will receive one.
So the easiest way is to find the acid.
Acids always have H leading the
formula when it comes to that molecule.
Um, so for example, I
have hydrochloric acid.
That was a strong acid.
I always recommend memorizing
your strong acids because it will
save you on a lot of questions.
So this one, what it's going to do
is because this is our acid, It will
donate its H plus to NH3 or ammonia.
Ammonia is a base.
Even though it has hydrogens on it, that
does not make it automatically a acid.
It has to have an acid at
the beginning of the formula.
So when that happens, well, what will
be left of HCl if it loses its proton?
Well, the only thing left is
going to be Cl minus remaining.
And then on the other side,
the NH3 is going to receive
a proton And become NH4 plus.
So we always have a plus and a minus
between these two different pieces.
So the acid donated its proton to
the base and the base accepted one.
If we continue to look at this, so
let's say if I do another one, well,
once again, we have HCl and water.
Water is unique.
Water can actually behave as
either an acid or a base completely
depending on what is it reacting with.
What is the strength of
what it is reacting with.
So if the other component, like HCL L
is really strong, then at then the acid
is gonna be its acid just like before.
So HCL is our acid.
So what it's gonna do is it's going
to donate, its proton to water.
So what's gonna be left of HCL L?
Well, we got rid of an H plus, so
the only thing left is CL minus.
And the reason it's CL minus is being
that we left an electron behind.
That means chlorine
has one extra electron.
So it might kind of help to see how
that entire Lewis structure looks like.
So kind of reminding you
of a really long time ago.
So if we have, let's say water and we
have the structure of HCl, well, that
proton is going to get transferred
And put on to the other water and as
a result, it's going to have an extra,
extra hydrogen and then chlorine is
going to have its negative charge.
So we'll have chlorine and then H3O
plus, which is known as hydronium.
So this is the hydronium ion and
then we have the chloride ion.
Okay.
So that's our acid.
and our base.
Let's look at one more.
So right now I have ammonia and water.
So ammonia is a very common base.
So that is one thing you want
to kind of keep in your head is
that ammonia is typically a base.
And like I said before, water can
act as either an acid or a base
depends on what it's interacting with.
If the other components are
stronger acid, then water is a base.
If the other component is a stronger
base, then water is an acid.
It's a little confusing, but
it will, you'll come over time.
So if water acts like an acid,
it's going to donate its proton.
So what is left?
Well, the only thing remaining is
going to be OH and OH8, and it'll be a
minus sign because we lost an H plus.
On the other side, we're
going to have NH4 plus.
For ammonium ion, ammonium and hydroxide.
So not only is this a, so if you kind of
look at this one particularly, so this, as
you saw ammonia is a Bronsted Lowry base.
Our Bronsted base and you can also see
that it produced hydroxide as a result.
So it also could be defined as something
that when it reacts with water.
So water could be defined as
something that could actually
increase the OH minus concentration.
So we'll kind of see that
the definitions will overlap.
So the way to remember
Bronsted base acids and bases.
I always kind of remember the little
mnemonic BAD, so with an extra A.
So Bases always accept,
Acids always donate.
So BAD, Bases accept, Acids donate,
when it comes to the protons,
is the easiest way to remember.
Let's go on to our next part.
So when it comes to the properties
of Acids and Bases, which was the
title of this video, it all comes
down to what observations have we
observed as chemists, as biologists,
over the course of hundreds of years.
Well, the first part is when it
comes to an acid is that they
generally have a very sour taste.
So one of the biggest examples that
you probably have on a weekly basis
is things that have citric acid in it.
So if you have oranges, lemons, limes,
or most soda products, um, like let's say
Sprite or orange soda or anything that's
like a fruitier flavor or lemon and lime.
Um, It generally has citric acid in it for
that flavor component that you're used to,
especially if you like anything that has
a sour, sour candy is that usually it's
covered with some citric acid to give that
like that, that mouth pucker feel to it.
Just like the picture of this
GIF of this girl up here.
Um, another thing is that a litmus
paper, which is something that's
commonly used in terms of, uh,
in biology and also in chemistry.
So what litmus paper is, it's a paper
that's coated with an indicator.
And what an indicator is, is that it's a
chemical that will change color depending
on essentially what it's reacting with.
So this one particularly has
a sensitivity to H or protons,
and hydroxide concentrations.
So if you have blue litmus paper and you
dip it in an acid, it's actually going
to cause it to turn red as a result.
So you'll see a color change happen.
Um, what other properties that there
are, that are really common too,
is that typically when it comes to
acids, they will react with different
metals to create hydrogen gas.
One of the common experiments that we
do in our own course is that we take
Magnesium reacted with HCl and then we
collect hydrogen in a really big glass
collection tube We also did an experiment
where if you take zinc and you react
it with HCl And then we collected the
hydrogen gas in a test tube and we lit
it on fire and it makes a pop sound
Right, they all make hydrogen now.
Another one is that being
that it acids and bases right?
They are electrolytes They will conduct
electricity in solutions, and this is
why how your, a lot of your car batteries
function is that they will have battery
acid inside of them to help them work.
Um, the other big thing that
happens as well is that they
react with a lot of carbonates
and bicarbonates to produce CO2.
So one of the big things that's
in soda is that you'll see that
they're on the ingredients.
There's carbonic acid.
Well, what carbonic acid does is
it's a gas evolution chemical.
So it will actually break down
into water and CO2, which is where
all that fizz and bubbles come
from, from carbonated beverages.
Let's look at the properties of bases.
So with the properties of bases,
these ones are tend to be very bitter.
They have a soapy feeling to them,
meaning that they're slippery.
They can even are described
as tasting soapy or chalky.
Um, one example of that chalky
taste is if you ever have a Tums,
which is an anti acid or antacid.
That will react with, uh, essentially
an acid, neutralize it when you,
if you have a really upset stomach,
but they usually taste chalky.
Um, other one, other things is that they
change color of the litmus paper as well.
So if you take, uh, let's say a red piece
of litmus paper, so there's two colors.
And you dip it into a
base, it will change blue.
Um, the other thing is that they
typically feel very slippery.
Now keep in mind with acids and bases,
you don't want to start tasting all
these different chemicals, right?
That was something I did in the early
1800s and 1900s and most of them didn't
really last super long afterwards.
That's not a safe thing to do.
Um, but if you do get some on your
skin, you feel it's all of a sudden
really slippery on your skin, wash your
hands for, for as long as to get those
chemicals off to keep yourself safe.
And then the last thing is they also
conduct electricity because they are.
Electrolytes, right?
So a strong electrolyte will
conduct a lot of electricity.
Um, whereas a weak electrolyte, not so
much because it does not dissociate fully.
Let's look at all of our definitions.
So when it comes to acids and bases,
there are three major definitions.
We went over two of them in this video.
The first one is the
Arrhenius acid and base.
This is essentially your, your
bare bones basic idea of how
to describe an acid and base.
This is usually what we use to
describe the pH or the p o h of
different solutions, something
you'll learn about in other videos.
So, whenever you have an Arrhenius acid,
it increases the proton concentration.
When you have an Arrhenius
base, it increases the hydroxide
concentration as a result.
When it comes to, let's say, the
Bronsted Lowry definition, what's
happening is that the acid is going to
be donating its H proton, to the base.
So, you're going to see
that getting increased.
traded right from one to the other.
The last one, which is not in this video,
but is very common in organic chemistry.
And something to be aware of if you
do have to go into Chem 1A, 1B in
organic, or if you're even in some of
the biological sciences, you might see
them is that there's another one called
Lewis acids and bases named after the
same scientists that did Lewis diagrams.
So the whole idea here is that essentially
it's all about electrons moving.
So a base typically donates electrons
and acid receives electrons, but this
is not in my course for introductory
chemistry, but I did want you to
know about the definition in case
you come across it and any of the
materials that you read about or study.
All right.
So these are your three definitions
in terms of acids and bases.
You do have to understand the idea
of Arrhenius, acids and bases and
the Bronsted Lowry acids and bases.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped you.
And if you have any questions, please
reach out to me and ask for help.
Um, if you, uh, are just watching
this video as another student and you
need help, please Please comment below
and let me know if there's anything I
can do, uh, and if this is also your
first time you're just watching, then
please like subscribe, comment, please.
And anything else, just let me know.
I am here for you.
And if you have suggestions
for future videos, let me know.
I'll try to make them for you.
All right.
Have a wonderful day and
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.